<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
	<lg n="146">
	  <l>Everyone who is committed to going step-by-step</l>
	  <l>along the completely correct <hi>Way</hi> of Lord Nr̥patuṅga.</l>
	  <l>will unfailingly be able to attain a rank that comes from</l>
	  <l>toiling on poetry of unsurpassable beauty by means of this system.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg n="147">
	  <l>Through the learnedness that comes from</l>
	  <l>serving the Young Woman who is Śruti</l>
	  <l>one who has understood without any gaps</l>
	  <l>the opinions and recommendations regarding ornaments </l>
	  <l>proclaimed by King Atiśayadhavaḷa,</l>
	  <l>will become the best among those who have fulfilled their duty.</l>
	  <note>
	    <p>This verse contains three words that are used elsewhere in the Way as titles of King Nr̥patuṅga: Atiśayadhavaḷa, Nītinirantara, and Kr̥takr̥tyamalla. If, however, we try to read them as titles in the present verse, we cannot produce a coherent meaning. The repetition of the titles, then, is only an “apparent repetition” (<hi>punaruktyābhāsa</hi>). We follow Seetharamaiah’s lead in reading two of these words in their literal senses, such that the verse as a whole functions as a phalaśruti, which speaks of the benefits of studying the Way. One such benefit is that the reader actually takes on the qualities that are embodied in Nr̥patuṅga’s titles.</p>
	  </note>
	</lg>
	<lg n="148">
	  <l>In the beauty of local speech, expression </l>
	  <l>is not allowed to exceed the idea</l>
	  <l>as if intending to conform to it.</l>
	  <l>The state of Sanskrit expressions serves as the standard</l>
	  <l>for Kannada speech without getting tangled up</l>
	  <l>in its intimidating syllables.</l>
	  <l>In this way, the system of Nītinirantara is put forth,</l>
	  <l>expansive and delicate, like a long creeping vine left to grow.</l>
	  <note>
	    <p>We take <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">melpu</foreign> in the sense of “delicateness,” although B uncharacteristically writes a long vowel (<foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">mēlpu</foreign>), which suggests that the word ought to be derived from <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">mēl</foreign> “above” (thus “superiority”) rather than <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">mel</foreign> “delicate.” This word, in our reading, suggests a contrast between the “beauty” (<foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">beḍaṅgu</foreign>) of local speech and the “intimidating” (<foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">vikaṭa-</foreign>) syllables of Sanskrit.</p>
	    <p>We also understand the word <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">padaṁ</foreign> to have a double meaning: as a <hi>dēśī</hi> word, it refers to the proper or mature state of something; as a <hi>samasaṁskṛta</hi> word, it refers to a word or expression.</p>
	    <p>For the phrase <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">dāṅguḍiviḍuva</foreign>, see Pampa, <hi>Bhārata</hi> 2.12.</p>
	  </note>
	</lg>
	<lg n="149">
	  <l>By manifesting different configurations of syllables, like a painter manifests</l>
	  <l>different combinations of colors, which sparkle with beauty and emotion,</l>
	  <l>poets enter into the storied divide between the realm of discourse</l>
	  <l>and the totality of the arts. In order to produce a work of art in speech,</l>
	  <l>poets must take this in hand: this method produced by Śrīvijaya.</l>
	  <note>
	    <p>This verse thematizes the close relationship of verbal and pictoral art, using the ornaments of a simile (“like a painter”) and, secondarily, “condensed expression” or <hi>samāsōkti</hi>: the word <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">varṇa</foreign> means “color” in the context of painting, and “syllable” in the context of poetry.</p>
	    <p>For <foreign xml:lang="kan-Latn">kaḷākaḷāpaka</foreign> see 3.229.</p>
	  </note>
	</lg>
	<trailer type="Colophon">
	  <ab>This</ab>
	</trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="2">
	<lg n="1">
	  <l>The qualities that beautify the body</l>
	  <l>of the supreme and excellent bride who is the work</l>
	  <l>are defined as unsurpassable ornaments,</l>
	  <l>well-known to the ancient poets.</l>
	  <note>
	    <p>This verse is an adaptation of the initial verse of the second chapter of Daṇḍin’s <hi>Mirror of Literature</hi>, which defines <foreign xml:lang="san-Latn">alaṁkāra</foreign>s or “ornaments” as “those qualities which impart beauty to a literary work” (<foreign xml:lang="san-Latn">kāvyaśōbhākarān dharmān alaṁkārān pracakṣatē</foreign>).</p>
	  </note>
	</lg>
	<lg n="2">
	  <l>In the assessment of the Ways </l>
	  <l>according to the analytical system </l>
	  <l>of the Beloved and Splendid Nr̥patuṅga,</l>
	  <l>the classification of the supreme ornaments,</l>
	  <l>which can appear in a wide variety of forms,</l>
	  <l>is twofold, according to the division into sound and sense.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg n="3">
	  <l>Moreover, to describe it in my own way,</l>
	  <l>the ornaments of sound should be considered first among these two.</l>
	  <l>Since they form the basis of the meaning, </l>
	  <l>they are more important and unique. </l>
	</lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
